<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true reporte of three straunge and wonderful accidents, lately hapened at Pernaw, a cittie in Lisslande Wherein is conteyned a prophesie of the greate dearth &amp; famine, which (by reason of the warres in those partes) hath there come to passe in the yeare last past, 1602. And also of the great victorie lately atchiued by the great Sophy, who with the aide &amp; assistance of the King of Persia, ouerthrew the Turkish emperour with all his forces neere vnto the riuer Euphrates. Truely translated out of the Dutch printed coppie, printed at Nimmegen.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857458</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857458</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23199</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23199)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1638:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true reporte of three straunge and wonderful accidents, lately hapened at Pernaw, a cittie in Lisslande Wherein is conteyned a prophesie of the greate dearth &amp; famine, which (by reason of the warres in those partes) hath there come to passe in the yeare last past, 1602. And also of the great victorie lately atchiued by the great Sophy, who with the aide &amp; assistance of the King of Persia, ouerthrew the Turkish emperour with all his forces neere vnto the riuer Euphrates. Truely translated out of the Dutch printed coppie, printed at Nimmegen.</title>
                  <author>Rappen, Francis, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[lower],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A variant of STC 19766.3, with different imprint.</note>
                  <note>In three parts; parts 2 and 3 each have special title page, with same imprint as general title page.</note>
                  <note>Includes A true copie of a letter written and sent from the castle of Ofel, which is signed: Francis Rappen the elder.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: @³ A-B⁴ (-@1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A True Reporte of three ſtraunge and wonderful Accidents, lately hapened at PERNAW, a Cittie in Lifflande.</p>
                  <p>Wherein is conteyned a Propheſie of the greate Dearth &amp; Famine, which (by reaſon of the warres in thoſe partes) hath there come to paſſe in the yeare laſt paſt, 1602.</p>
                  <p>And alſo of the great Victorie lately atchiued by the great Sophy, who with the aide &amp; aſſiſtance of the King of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, ouerthrew the Turkiſh Emperour with all his forces neere vnto thé Riuer Euphrates.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device: woman (?) holding book and large palm</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> At London printed by R. B 1603.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>robed figure with staff in left hand</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:2"/>
                  <head>¶ A true Report of three ſtrange accidents which lately happened at Pernaw, a Cittie in Lifflandé &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E finde (gentle reader) in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Hiſtories, and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the workes of that famous and learned writer <hi>Flauius Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus lib. 7. cap. 12.</hi> that before the lamentable and woful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Hieruſalem, there appeared many ſtrange ſignes both in the aire, and among the people, namely there was ſeene right about the ſaid Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a dreadfull Starre, in forme and faſhion of a Sword: as alſo that in the darke night cleare day appeared and was ſeene in the Temple: that a Cow brought forth a Lambe, and which was moſt ſtrange, a certaine man went vp and downe among the people, continually for the ſpace of ſeauen yeares before, not ceaſing with wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cries, to forwarne and admoniſh the people to forſake their wickednes: fore ſhewing the deſtruction of the place.</p>
                  <p>The very like, yea and almoſt the verie ſame acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents ſignes and wonders, haue lately happened within this whilome moſt pleaſante Countrie of <hi>Livonia,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:23199:3"/>the Cittie of <hi>Pernaw:</hi> for in the yeare <hi>1599.</hi> vppon Saint Lukes day, a certaine Merchant of the ſaid Cittie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (according to the cuſtome of the Countrie) enuited many of his freinds and Neighbours to a feaſt at his houſe, among the reſt alſo, enuited thither a certaine old man of the ſame Cittie whoſe name was <hi>Stile,</hi> a man of the age of foure ſcore yeares or thereabout, knowne to all the inhabitants there to be borne deafe and dumbe, and had ſoe continued all his life tyme to that day.</p>
                  <p>This olde man being placed at the table among the company, and ſeing the great and horrible abuſe of the good guiftes and creatures of God which were there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, by thoſe abhominable vices of gluttony and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, and not being able to endure the ſight therof, by the iuſt iudgment of God preſently leapt ouer the Table, and with a fierce and ſterne countenance, turning his eyes toward the people, and wringing his hands as a ſigne of the great ſorrow which he conceiued at his hart, burſt forth in theſe ſpeaches to the Companie which were preſent.</p>
                  <p>Alas quoth he (my deare freinds) how can you be thus merrie, when a man ſeeing this abhominable abuſe, to the high diſpleaſure of almightie God, might well loathe to liue any longer in ſo wicked a time. Therfore (deare brethren and ſiſters) repent, repent I ſay, for the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Lord God is neare at hand: with greate ſtormes and ouerflowing waters, wil he deſtroy the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and nothing but affliction and punniſhment ſhalbe their portion.</p>
                  <p>Such dearth that yeare ſhalbe that the people ſhall not finde any foode for nouriſhment, nor any way to eſcape by reaſon of the troubleſome warre to come: great plague peſtilence and murren ſhall deſtroy both younge and old, therfore liue ye as if preſently ye ſhould die, for ſurely it is at hand: great and horrible wonders ſhall ye heare,
<pb facs="tcp:23199:3"/>and ſée many ſtrange and monſtrous Children borne, as a looking-glaſſe both for rich and poore.</p>
                  <p>The people with great admiration and aſtoniſhment came running together to ſee this miracle which had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penned, and the Company which were enuited being daſht with this ſuddaine accident, haueing now giuen ouer their paſtime and being ſore amaſed were with one accord attentiue to the ſpeaches of the olde man, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aſwell by his ſtrange geſtures as by the ſuddainnes of his ſpeach that this was Gods onely doings: and being moued with great feare and horror, asked him at what time all thoſe things ſhould happen: wheruppon the ſaid dumbe man thus preſentlie replied.</p>
                  <p>Ere the yeare <hi>99</hi> be come and paſt, the Lord God in his iuſt anger and wrath will draw his ſword, therfore repent you of your ſinnes, for the day of iudgment is at hand.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words ſpoken, the man was againe bereft of his ſpeach, and became dumbe as before, feeling him ſelfe preſently ſicke, and the next day after he died: and was honorably buried, being accompanied to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, by an infinite number of the inhabitantes there, whoe greatly lamented for his death.</p>
                  <p>The next day after his buriall, there was a certaine woman brought forth a man childe, with a naturall face before, and behind like the ſcull of a dead man, his right arme alſo was like a Sword, and the other like a Rodde: which child liued two dayes and no longer.</p>
                  <p>After this the Lord ſhewed an other, no leſſe fearefull ſigne of his indignation and wrath, for iuſt ouer the ſaid Cittie of <hi>Pernaw,</hi> was perfectly ſeene in the cleare Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament or Skie, a Béere and Coffin, couered all with blacke: which ſight endured from foure of the clocke in the afternoone, till eleuen in the ſame Night.</p>
                  <p>Therefore good chriſtians, conſider firſt the ſuddaine
<pb facs="tcp:23199:4"/>and fearefull ſpéech of the Dumbe, ſecondly, looke vppon the monſtrous birth and ſhape of this Childe, and laſtly, meditate vppon the fearfull ſigne ſéene in the Ayre, and therevpon with an humble and penitent hart, imagine the Tragicall end of all, pittying the afflicted Countrey and people of <hi>Lyffeland,</hi> and let their hard fortune be a warning to thee, that thou ſinne no more preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
                  <p>And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen <hi>Poet</hi> ſayeth. <hi>Foelix que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaciunt aliena pericula cautum,</hi> that is to ſaye, happy is he which can beware by other mens perilles: make thy ſelfe happie with this warning, and doe not with the wicked and ſtubborne Iewes, contemne and ſcorne, this gentle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and fore-warning of the Dumbe, leaſt God in his Iuſtice bring a worſe Plague vpon vs, then he did eyther vpon thoſe Iewes or vppon this Countrey of <hi>Lyffeland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:4"/>
                  <p>A True Reporte of the great Victorie lately atchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the great SOPHY: who with the aide and aſſiſtance of the the king of Perſia, ouerthrew the Turkiſh Emperour with all his forces, neere vnto the riuer Euphrates.</p>
                  <p>Truly tranſlated out of the high Dutch Copie printed at Hamborrow. 1602.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device: woman (?) holding book and large palm</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>At London printed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1603.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:5"/>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:23199:5"/>
                  <head>¶ A true Report, of the late victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie atchiued by the great Sophy: together with the king of Perſia, vpon the Turkes &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the great Turkiſh Emperour with all his Armie, munition, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, was come to the Ryuer of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> being ſtrong both of Horſe &amp; foot, about three hundred Thouſand men, and perceauing that <hi>Morath</hi> generall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Perſians,</hi> had cauſed the Bridge to be pulled down there, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was made ouer the ſaid Riuer, and that he was marched on th'other ſide, and hard by a mountaine did prepare and ſtrengthen himſelfe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forces ſent vnto him by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great <hi>Sophy,</hi> with thoſe hee had before, ſo that the <hi>Perſians</hi> were ſtronge about Foure-ſcore and tenne Thouſand men, amongſt the which were about twenty Thouſand, whereof every one of them, had two horſes for a man.</p>
                  <p>The Turke could not haue ſo much inteligence to vnderſtand if the <hi>Sophy</hi> himſelfe were perſonally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Campe, or no: or if he yet were in <hi>Perſia</hi> for more forces, which he eſpecially did feare.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe therfore he could not paſſe ouer the Riuer,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23199:6"/>he in all haſt cauſed the bridge to be builded againe, and ſent ouer the ſaid Riuer two Genneralls called <hi>Beller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes</hi> with their forces, to wit <hi>Bellerby</hi> of <hi>Gretia</hi> and <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerby</hi> of <hi>Natolia,</hi> but he himſelfe tarried on this ſide of the water till the next morning.</p>
                  <p>Now about two houres before day breaking the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Moreth</hi> fell in the Campe of <hi>Bellerby</hi> of <hi>Grecia,</hi> who had encamped himſelfe ſomwhat farre off from the <hi>Bellerby</hi> of <hi>Natolia,</hi> and moſt valiently came vppon him with ſuch a force and power, that he vppon a ſoddaine moſt ſpéedily did ouercome all his Enſignes and Lents, and ouerthrew and ſlew all his Campe.</p>
                  <p>The Soldiers of the Campe of the <hi>Bellerby</hi> of <hi>Natolia</hi> héerwitha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ll were put in ſuch a feare, that they ranne in to the Riuer, and paſſed ouer to the Campe of the great Turke,</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Turke</hi> ſéeing this ill ſucceſſe, preſently planted his Ordenaunce in good order one by an other, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſame right againſt the Enemie which was on the other ſide of the water: and becauſe they thould not ſée the Ordinaunce, he commaunded that ſome Companies ſhould be placed and ſtand before the ſaid Ordinance, with this token, that when the peices of Ordinance ſhould be all in readines and charged, they ſhould ſound Alarme and the ſaid Companies ſtanding before the ſaid Ordinance ſhould part aſide, and ſo to diſcharge the ſaid peices of Ordinance vppon the Enemie.</p>
                  <p>This determination being agréed vppon, and fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put to the aforeſaid Ordenance, many of them did hurſt and fly abroad, and ſlew and hurt a notable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men, yea and many of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Armie: by the noiſe, cry, and tumult wherof, many Horſes and Mules, with thoſe that were on the backs of them did leape into the Riuer and were drowned,</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:23199:6"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Sophians</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> which had ſuſtained great loſſe of men by means of the Ordinance, retired on the other ſide of the Mountaine, and it was ſuppoſed that at that time were ſlaine and ſhot to death about Twentie thouſand <hi>Sophians</hi> and <hi>Perſians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They retireing ſo backwards as is aforeſaid, the <hi>Turke</hi> with all his whole Armie paſſed ouer the Riuer, and marched towards the Mountaine where the <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were encamped, who had deuided themſelues into foure partes or ſquadrons, kéeping cloſe together: and when they ſawe that the <hi>Turkes</hi> came vppon them, they were glad, and moſt valiently met and ſought with them ſo that on both ſides many men were ſlaine: but the night ouertooke them, which was to the aduantage of the <hi>Sophians</hi> for it was not poſſible that they could reſiſt and withſtand and lounger againſt the great force and power of the Turkes, therefore by Night they all did flye to the Mountaine, the Turkes for darkeneſſe could not follow them, as they were minded and would faine haue done and ſo the Turke tarrying in the fieldes that Night pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and concluded the next day to leaue all his footemen with the péeces of Ordinance behind him and with horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men onely to purſue the Enemies and by theſe meanes vnawares to ſurpriſe and take the Towne of <hi>Tauris,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe of the Towne ſhould heare of the ouerthrowe of the <hi>Sophy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But on the other ſide, the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Sophians,</hi> which dilligently did looke to themſelues, and had great care to the matter, concluded with themſelues, that ten thouſand men which were the day before newly ariued, ſhould marche againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and when the <hi>Turkes</hi> ſhould come vppon them, they ſhould flee, as if they voyce ouercome, and the reſt of the <hi>Sophians</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which were yet about twentie thouſand, ſhould come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23199:7"/>the <hi>Turks,</hi> and compaſſed them betwéen them both, and without doubte they ſhould ſpéed well, and ouercome their enemies. The next morning, the <hi>Turke</hi> ſéeing that the enimie was yet ſo neare at hand, he thought they had not bin able to fly any further for darknes, came vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with great force: but they preſently according to their agréement did fly, and the <hi>Turkes</hi> not thinking on this martial pollicie, did purſue them till noone, and being come to a ſmall Riuer, becauſe they were ſomwhat wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and tired, encamped themſelues on the ſaid Riuers ſide and there dined: and after dinner the freſh <hi>Turkes</hi> leauing the wearied and tyred Companies with all their treaſures and ſpoiles behinde them, thinking the next night vnawares to ſurprize the Towne of <hi>Tauris,</hi> did purſue and chaſe the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Sophians,</hi> in their fained flight.</p>
                  <p>But when they came to the Towne, in all haſt a poſt came to the great <hi>Turke</hi> about two houres in the night, who certified vnto him that the ennimie had ouerthrown and ſlaine all his footemen which he had left behinde, and that they had gotten the pieces of Ordinance, and ſtill were coming with all their forces behinde him.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Turke</hi> hearing ſuche newes, and thinking on the great treaſure that he had left behind him, preſently went back againe, and the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Sophians</hi> which héertofore did flie, turned alſo backe againe, and ſawe that their forces did follow and purſue the <hi>Turks</hi> behinde. The <hi>Turkes</hi> which tarried with the treaſure on the ſaid water ſide, perceiuing their Enemies did breake vp and runne away, the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Sophians</hi> being before and behinde the <hi>Turkes,</hi> came fiercely and valiantly vppon them, and did great hurt amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>The great <hi>Turke</hi> much diſcontented, ſéeing that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23199:7"/>Ennemie had ſo craftilie compaſſed and brought him in the middle betwéene them, begun a moſt harde and hote battaile, wherin the <hi>Sophians</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> got the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: which when the <hi>Turkes</hi> ſaw, they did fly out on the one ſide, for otherwiſe it was not poſſible for them to eſcape.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperour himſelfe, when he ſawe that all his forces did fly, and that all his Enſignes were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, did likewiſe fly to ſaue his life, and came with a moſt ſwifte horſe to <hi>Amaſia,</hi> and tarried in <hi>Natolia</hi> till the romnant of his Armie (which was verie little) was gathered together: for the Turkes did nothing but flie all the Night, and al thoſe which were ſlack in running, were all cut downe: and thoſe that came ouer the Riuer pulled downe the bridge made by them before, to the end the <hi>Perſians</hi> ſhould not purſue them: but the <hi>Pérſians</hi> and <hi>Sophians</hi> being glad of the victorie, as Conquerours of the fielde, went home againe: although they would faine haue proſecuted their victorie, had not the moſt part of their forces been ſlaine</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Performed in Anno Domini. 1602</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:8"/>
                  <p>A True and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reporte of the miſerable &amp; pitifull preſent ſtate of the Cuntrey of LIVONIA, (commonly called <hi>Lyffelande</hi>) concerning the great Dearth &amp; Famine now being there, [by reaſon of the VVarres] in ſuch ſorte that one Neighbour and Friende doth kill an other and eate them, the like neuer before, eyther ſeene or hearde of. (⸫)</p>
                  <p>Written by credible &amp; great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages of that Cuntrey, vnto the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned <hi>Conrado Schluſſelborrow,</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie, and Superintendant in the Citty of Stralſunde in Suetia.</p>
                  <p>Truly tranſlated out of the high Dutch Copie printed at Hamborrow. 1602.</p>
                  <p>¶ At London printed by R. B. 1603.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:9"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:23199:9"/>
                  <head>¶ A true Relation of the miſerable and pitifull ſtate of the Cuntrey of L. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VONIA, aſſicted with great Dearth Famine &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Reuerend and learned Doctor, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſeruing at this preſent time I coulde not omitte to certifie vnto your worſhip the lamentable and pittifull eſtate of this ſore afflicted country of Lyffland, for ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the iuſt wrath of God by reaſon of our manifold ſinnes, is kindled againſt vs.</p>
                  <p>And firſt by reaſon of theſe warrs, many thouſand men were ſlaine and put to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworde on both ſides, as wel <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, Dutchmen, Swedens, Polonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:</hi> as alſo other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, amongſt the which many without any reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſexe or age moſt truelly were racked, martyred and burned, yea the fruite in the Mothers Wombe was not ſpared, the little Infants were taken and held vp by the féete, and without any mercie moſt barbarouſly maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and cut into péeces.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, there was héere ſuch wonderful and ſtrang diſeaſes and ſickneſſes almoſt amongſt al men, that they did fall down in the ſtréetes and fieldes, &amp; became madde and ſenceleſſe yea and the moſt part died thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:23199:10"/>
                  <p>Thirdly there was neuer ſuch great dearth &amp; famine, eſpecially amongſt the poore Huſbandman and Countrie folke, inſomuch that Many did eate the dead carions that they found in the fields, as Horſes, Cats, Dogges, &amp; alſo the very ſhoes of their féete, yea one Chriſtian body hath eaten an other: and eſpecially which is moſt wonderfull and neuer heard of before. That in the Towne of <hi>Salis</hi> two Daughters did eate their deſeaſed Father, and alſo a woman did eate her deſeaſed huſbande. And at another place one neighbour ſent his child to one of his neighbors to fetch or carry ſomthing, who tooke the child and cut his throate, and whileſt he was taking out the intrailes, the Father of the child [who die maruell of the long tarrying of his Childe came and perceauing that his Childe was ſlaughtered in manner aforeſayd, was in a mighty rage, &amp; fought with his neighbour who likewiſe killed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child, &amp; dreſſed him for meate &amp; eate him. Such feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and heauy accidentes doe daylye happen with vs in <hi>Lyffland.</hi> God almighty moſt graciouſly deliuer vs and ſhew his mercy vpon vs.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dated</hi> at <hi>Pernaw,</hi> 
                        <date>the fourth of September. <hi>Anno 1602.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:23199:10"/>
                  <head>¶ A true Copie of a Letter written &amp; ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t from the Caſtle of Oſel, of the miſerable eſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> at this préſent time of Lyffland: Written by M. Frauncis Rappen the elder Gentl. vnto the reuerend father M. Peter Dvd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtedten, Preacher in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cittie of new Pernaw. (⸫)</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerend and learned father, Friend and Kinſman. I and all my houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with all our harts are very ſory and moſt pittifully grieued to he are the miſerable eſtate, which you by reaſon of the fearefull raiſing of warres, haue ſuſtayned, we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe here in theſe places are troubled and plagued with famine (God Almighty ſhew his mercy vppon vs, and ſaue vs and deliuer vs from it) inſomuch that if it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God we had rather to chooſe a plague for it. Séeing that not onely the poore people ſtaruing and famiſhing do fall downe and die in the ſtréetes and wayes, going one neighbour to an other, and doe ſtill ſtriue and fight for dead cattell which die of the murren, and moſt gree dely doe eate the carions of the fleide and doe not regard how
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23199:11"/>vnnaturall it is to deuoure dead ſwyne, dogges &amp; catte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> but alſo one Chriſtian and friend killeth &amp; eateth another, the parents doe dreſſe for meate their children when they are dead by reaſon of the great Dearth, for the Enemie hath waſted: ſpoiled all the Countrie; and robbed euery one of their goods, for which cauſes you haue béene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to go w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your wife and familie out of theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries into <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And although wée would faine giue double money for Corne, wée can here get none ſéeing all is gone, partly ſpoiled and waſted vpon the Fieldes, and partly by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the cold Summer it could not ripe, inſomuch that all my Tennantes cannot furniſh nor prouide me of a buſhel of corne to releeue my poore familie, who for very hunger do ſtarue and famiſh which moſt pittifully doeth greeue my harte.</p>
                  <p>I pray the Lord of Heauen mercifully to looke vppon vs, and deliuer vs from this moſt lamentable eſtate.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dated</hi> at <hi>Oſel</hi> 
                        <date>the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>September. 1602.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your worſhips friend Francis Rappen the elder.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23199:11"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
